Finding aid to Office of the President Herbert John Davis files CA.MS.00011
Smith College Archives
Office of the President Herbert John Davis Files
1939-1951
Smith College Archives
Davis, Herbert John, 1893-1967.
CA.MS.00011
3.958 linear feet (10 containers)
Herbert John Davis was the fourth president of Smith College, professor of English and world-renowned expert on Jonathan Swift. Contains correspondence, newspaper articles, and memorabilia related to his official duties as President of Smith College.
Biographical / Historical
Herbert John Davis was born on May 24, 1893 in Northamptonshire, England, where he received his elementary and secondary education. He later attended Oxford University (St. John's College) from which he graduated in 1914. He then served in France and Belgium during WWI and in 1919 he returned to Oxford to earn his A.M. In 1922, Davis married Gertrude Lucas of Opladen, Rheinland, Germany but she died tragically just six years later. In 1930, Davis married Gladys Wookey of Toronto and the couple had two daughters, Charlotte Elisabeth Ann and Jane.
In 1920, Davis acquired a position at the University of Leeds where he taught for two years. He then moved to the University of Toronto where he remained for sixteen years. He was hired as an Associate Professor of English, and was later promoted to a full Professor. He also served as chair the English Department at Toronto. In 1938 Davis accepted a position as Chair of the English department at Cornell University.
In 1939, Davis succeeded William Allan Neilson as president of Smith College and he assumed this role for the 1940-1941 school year. Davis served as the fourth president of Smith College until 1949 when he returned to Oxford as a reader in textual criticism. Davis retired from Oxford in 1960.
During his academic career Davis made several notable contributions to academia. Following his passion for poetry and prose, Davis became a world renowned expert on Jonathan Swift and wrote several books on his work including Swift's View of Poetry (1931) and Stella, a Gentlewoman of the Eighteenth Century (1942). The latter is an account of the friendship that existed between Swift and Esther Johnson. Davis also edited the fourteen volume work, The Prose Works of Jonathan Swift (1939-68). Davis' distinguished literary contributions were well recognized and he received several honorary degrees including a Doctorate of Laws from Amherst College in 1940.
In addition to his enthusiasm for the English language, Davis was also extremely socially conscious and particularly concerned with WWII raging overseas. Perhaps his most memorable act of charity was providing a home to five British refugee children for several years during the war. Many of his colleagues and friends followed his lead and opened their doors to children in need. Davis died on March 28, 1967.
Scope and Contents
Office of the President Herbert John Davis Files document his official duties as President of Smith College. The collection includes correspondence, newspaper articles, and memorabilia. Materials document the running of the College and the relationship of the Office of the President with the various academic departments and committees. Of interest is correspondence about the 75th anniversary celebration of the college; committee work including Trustee, faculty and administrative committees; the Junior Year Abroad program at Smith; and correspondence with U.S. government officials concerning the WAVES program on campus.
Related Material
For further information about activities of Davis' during his Smith College presidency see also the President's Reports. For more information about the academic career and personal life of Herbert John Davis see the Herbert John Davis Personal Papers in the College Archives.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These papers were transferred to the College Archives from the Office of the President after President Davis left the College in 1949.
Smith College -- presidents; Davis, Herbert John, 1893-1967.; Smith College--Faculty.; Smith College--Presidents.; Neilson, William Allan, 1869-1946.; Comstock, Ada Louise.; Morrow, Elizabeth, 1873-1955.; Smith College. Office of President.
- A, General Correspondence, 1940-45; 1947-48; 1950; undated (Box 454, Folder 1)
  - Abramowicz, Dina, 1946 (Box 454, Folder 2)
  - Academic Departments-Art, 1940-48; undated (Box 454, Folder 3)
  - Academic Departments-Astronomy, 1941-47 (Box 454, Folder 4)
  - Academic Departments-Botany, 1941-44 (Box 454, Folder 5)
  - Academic Departments-Chemistry, 1941-48 (Box 454, Folder 6)
  - Academic Departments-Classics, 1942-44; undated (Box 454, Folder 7)
  - Academic Departments-Economics, 1940-44 (Box 454, Folder 8)
  - Academic Departments-Education, 1941-47; undated (Box 454, Folder 9)
  - Academic Departments-English, 1941-47 (Box 454, Folder 10)
  - Academic Departments-French, 1940-47 (Box 454, Folder 11)
  - Academic Departments-Geology, 1941-48 (Box 454, Folder 12)
  - Academic Departments-German, 1941-47; undated (Box 454, Folder 13)
  - Academic Departments-Government, 1941-47 (Box 454, Folder 14)
  - Academic Departments-History, 1941-47 (Box 454, Folder 15)
  - Academic Departments-Hygiene and Bacteriology, 1940-47 (Box 454, Folder 16)
  - Academic Departments-Italian, 1942-44 (Box 454, Folder 17)
  - Academic Departments-Mathematics, 1941-47 (Box 454, Folder 18)
  - Academic Departments-Music, 1940-47 (Box 454, Folder 19)
  - Academic Departments-Philosophy, 1941-44 (Box 454, Folder 20)
  - Academic Departments-Physical Education, 1941-46; undated (Box 454, Folder 21)
  - Academic Departments-Physics, 1940-47 (Box 454, Folder 22)
  - Academic Departments-Psychology, 1941-47 (Box 454, Folder 23)
  - Academic Departments-Religion, 1941-44 (Box 454, Folder 24)
  - Academic Departments-Slavic Languages, 1944 (Box 454, Folder 25)
  - Academic Departments-Sociology, 1941-47 (Box 454, Folder 26)
  - Academic Departments-Spanish, 1941-47 (Box 454, Folder 27)
  - Academic Departments-Speech, 1941-44 (Box 454, Folder 28)
  - Academic Departments-Theater and Dance, 1941-49; undated (Box 454, Folder 29)
  - Academic Departments-Zoology, 1941-49; undated (Box 454, Folder 30)
  - Administration-Nyman Report, 1942 (Box 454, Folder 31)
  - Adopt-A-Town Committee, 1941 (Box 454, Folder 32)
  - Alumnae Association, 1940-48 (Box 454, Folder 33)
  - Alumnae Clubs, 1940-47 (Box 454, Folder 34)
  - Anniversary 1950 (75th) Conference on the Role of Women in Contemporary Society, 1946-47 (Box 454, Folder 35)
  - Anniversary 1950 (75th) Fund-General, 1945-49; undated (Box 454, Folder 36)
  - Anniversary 1950 (75th) Fund-Campaign Director (Byron Shimp), 1946-49 (Box 455, Folder 1)
  - Anniversary 1950 (75th) Fund-Grant Foundation, 1946-47 (Box 455, Folder 2)
  - Anniversary 1950 (75th) Fund-Nat'l Broadcasting Company, 1948-49 (Box 455, Folder 3)
  - Anniversary 1950 (75th) Fund-Planning Committee, 1945 (Box 455, Folder 4)
  - Anniversary 1950 (75th) Fund-Publicity Committee, 1946 (Box 455, Folder 5)
  - Anniversary 1950 (75th) Fund-Publicity Director (Charles Miller), Feb-Oct 1946 (Box 455, Folder 6)
  - Anniversary 1950 (75th) Fund-Public Relations Program (Theodore Swanson), 1 Nov 1946-47 (Box 455, Folder 7)
  - Anniversary 1950 (75th) Fund-Trustee Committee, 1946-49; undated (Box 455, Folder 8)
  - Architecture-Competition Dormitory (proposed), 1945-47 (Box 455, Folder 9)
  - Archives/Sophia Smith Collection, 1940-48; undated (Box 455, Folder 10)
  - Assembly, 1942-50; undated (Box 455, Folder 11)
  - Association of American Colleges, 1941-43 (Box 455, Folder 12)
- B, General Correspondence, 1943-44; 1946-49; 1951 (Box 455, Folder 13)
  - Beard, Mary Ritter, 1941 (Box 455, Folder 14)
  - Botanic Garden, 1943; 1947 (Box 455, Folder 15)
  - British War Relief Society, 1940-41 (Box 455, Folder 16)
  - Bryn Mawr, 1941-48 (Box 455, Folder 17)
  - Buildings and Grounds, 1940-49; undated (Box 455, Folder 18)
  - Buildings and Grounds-Chapel (proposed), 1942-49; undated (Box 455, Folder 19)
  - Buildings and Grounds-Deanery (proposed), 1941-42; undated (Box 455, Folder 20)
  - Buildings and Grounds-Infirmary-Additions, 1942-50 (Box 456, Folder 1)
  - Buildings and Grounds-John M. Greene Hall Alterations, 30 Oct 1943-30 Jun 1949 (Box 456, Folder 2)
  - Buildings and Grounds-Report on Adequacy of Dormitories and Classrooms, 1949 (Box 456, Folder 3)
- C, General Correspondence, 1940-1944; 1947-49 (Box 456, Folder 4)
  - Cambridge School of Architecture and Landscape Architecture, 1939-43 (Box 456, Folder 5)
  - Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching, 1941-44 (Box 456, Folder 6)
  - College Cevenol, 1946-48 (Box 456, Folder 7)
  - College Entrance Examination Board, 1941-44 (Box 456, Folder 8)
  - Commencement, 1941-49 (Box 456, Folder 9)
  - Committees-General, 1942-46 (Box 456, Folder 10)
  - Committees-Acceleration, 1942-43; undated (Box 456, Folder 11)
  - Committees-Administrative Board, 1941-43 (Box 456, Folder 12)
  - Committees-Board of Admission, 1941-45 (Box 456, Folder 13)
  - Committees-Board of Advisors, 1943; undated (Box 456, Folder 14)
  - Committees-on the Calendar, 1947 (Box 456, Folder 15)
  - Committees-to Choose a Dean, 1946-47 (Box 456, Folder 16)
  - Committees-on Committees, 1942-47 (Box 456, Folder 17)
  - Committees-(Faculty-Trustee) Conference, 1948-49 (Box 456, Folder 18)
  - Committees-on Defense and Reconstruction, 1942 (Box 456, Folder 19)
  - Committees-Emergency Committee on Faculty Salaries, 1947-48 (Box 456, Folder 20)
  - Committees-Emergency Council, 1941-42; undated (Box 456, Folder 21)
  - Committees-Fine Arts, 1946-47 (Box 456, Folder 22)
  - Committees-on Foreign Students, 1943-49 (Box 456, Folder 23)
  - Committees-Funds to Attend Learned Societies, 1942-43 (Box 456, Folder 24)
  - Committees-on Graduate Study, 1941-49; undated (Box 456, Folder 25)
  - Committees-on Honors, 1941-44 (Box 456, Folder 26)
  - Committees-on Hygiene, undated (Box 456, Folder 27)
  - Committees-on the Hymn Book, 1941 (Box 456, Folder 28)
  - Committees-on the Library, 1943-44 (Box 456, Folder 29)
  - Committees-on Planning, 1944-46 (Box 456, Folder 30)
  - Committees-on Post-War Planning, 1944-46; undated (Box 457, Folder 1)
  - Committees-on Refugee Fellowships, 1940-43 (Box 457, Folder 2)
  - Committees-on Resources, 1940-45; undated (Box 457, Folder 3)
  - Committees-on Scholarships, 1942 (Box 457, Folder 4)
  - Committees-on Special Assistance in Written English, 1943-44; undated (Box 457, Folder 5)
  - Committees-on Summer Work, 1942-43; undated (Box 457, Folder 6)
  - Committees-on Teaching and Promotion, 1942-44 (Box 457, Folder 7)
  - Committees-on Tenure and Promotion, 1942-44
  - Committees-on War Minors, 1942-43 (Box 457, Folder 9)
  - Conference-Eighteenth Century Conference, 1946-47 (Box 457, Folder 10)
  - Conference-New England Conference on Renaissance Studies, 1946 (Box 457, Folder 11)
  - Conference-The Pompeiiana, 1942 (Box 457, Folder 12)
  - Conference-The Pompeiiana, 1948 (Box 457, Folder 13)
  - Conference-on Southern New England, 1942 (Box 457, Folder 14)
  - Connecticut College, 1944 (Box 457, Folder 15)
  - Council of Industrial Studies, 1942-48 (Box 457, Folder 16)
- D, General Correspondence, 1940-44; 1947; undated (Box 457, Folder 17)
  - Day School, 1942-49; undated (Box 457, Folder 18)
  - Dean, Class, 1942-43; undated (Box 457, Folder 19)
  - Dean, Office of, 1941-45 (Box 457, Folder 20)
- E, General Correspondence, 1941-44; 1948 (Box 457, Folder 21)
  - Employment, Office of, 1943-49; undated (Box 457, Folder 22)
  - Experiment in International Living, Inc., 1942-48 (Box 457, Folder 23)
- F, General Correspondence, 1939-44; 1946; 1950 (Box 457, Folder 24)
  - Faculty-General, 1941-47 (Box 457, Folder 25)
  - Faculty-Sabbaticals, 1944-49; undated (Box 457, Folder 26)
  - Faculty-Salaries, 1946-47; undated (Box 458, Folder 1)
  - Faculty-Secretary of, 1940-46 (Box 458, Folder 2)
  - Ferrand, Beatrix, 1942 (Box 458, Folder 3)
  - Faulkner, Harold Underwood, 1940-47; undated (Box 458, Folder 4)
  - Food Service (Report on Study of the Feeding Operation), 1948 (Box 458, Folder 5)
  - Francis, Ann, 1939-40; 1942 (Box 458, Folder 6)
- G, General Correspondence, 1946-47 (Box 458, Folder 7)
  - Genetics Experiment Station, 1942-49 (Box 458, Folder 8)
  - Greene, Helen French (1891), 1941; 1943; 1947 (Box 458, Folder 9)
- H, General Correspondence, 1940-42 (Box 458, Folder 10)
  - Harlow, S. Ralph, 1942-46 (Box 458, Folder 11)
  - Hirschorn, Hannah (Scharps), 1942-43 (Box 458, Folder 12)
  - Hofer, Philip, 1947 (Box 458, Folder 13)
  - Honorary Degrees, 1941-47 (Box 458, Folder 14)
  - Honors Program, 1940-47; undated (Box 458, Folder 15)
- I, General Correspondence, 1942-43; 1945 (Box 458, Folder 16)
  - Infirmary, 1941-49 (Box 458, Folder 17)
  - Institute of International Education, 1941-48 (Box 458, Folder 18)
  - International Student Service, 1941-47 (Box 458, Folder 19)
- J, General Correspondence, 1942-44; 1948; undated (Box 458, Folder 20)
  - Jacob, Cary, 1942-44 (Box 458, Folder 21)
  - Junior Year Abroad-General, 1946-49; undated (Box 458, Folder 22)
  - Junior Year Abroad-France, 1946-48 (Box 459, Folder 1)
  - Junior Year Abroad-Geneva, 1946-49 (Box 459, Folder 2)
  - Junior Year Abroad-Italy, 1946-49 (Box 459, Folder 3)
  - Junior Year Abroad-Mexico, 1940-49 (Box 459, Folder 4)
  - Junior Year Abroad-Toronto, 1945-46 (Box 459, Folder 5)
  - Juniper Lodge, 1941-44; undated (Box 459, Folder 6)
- K, General Correspondence, 1941-44; 1947-48 (Box 459, Folder 7)
  - Kane, Mrs. R. Keith, 1941-43; 1947; undated (Box 459, Folder 8)
  - Kusaka, Shuichi, 1943-44 (Box 459, Folder 9)
- L, General Correspondence, 1940-42 (Box 459, Folder 10)
  - Lamont, Florence (Corliss), 1942-48 (Box 459, Folder 11)
  - Landscape Architect,Office of, 1941-43 (Box 459, Folder 12)
  - Lee, Gerald and Jeannette, 1941-45 (Box 459, Folder 13)
  - Lee, Rensselaer Wright, 1941-44 (Box 459, Folder 14)
  - Library, 1940-49; undated (Box 459, Folder 15)
  - Library, Friends of, 1941-42 (Box 459, Folder 16)
- M, General Correspondence, 1940-42 (Box 459, Folder 17)
  - Massachusetts Audubon Society, 1944-47 (Box 459, Folder 18)
  - McCauley, William Steele, 1942-43 (Box 459, Folder 19)
  - Mount Holyoke College, 1941-49 (Box 459, Folder 20)
  - Museum of Art, 1940-49; undated (Box 459, Folder 21)
- N, General Correspondence, 1942-44; 1947 (Box 460, Folder 1)
  - National Council of American-Soviet Friendship, 1943-49 (Box 460, Folder 2)
  - National Japanese-American Student Relocation Committee, 1942-43 (Box 460, Folder 3)
  - Navy League of the United States, 1942 (Box 460, Folder 4)
  - Neilson, Elisabeth Muser, 1940-49; undated (Box 460, Folder 5)
  - Neilson, William Allan, 1942-46 (Box 460, Folder 6)
  - Northampton-General, 1940-46 (Box 460, Folder 7)
  - Northampton-Academy of Music, 1942-44 (Box 460, Folder 8)
  - Nursery School, 1947 (Box 460, Folder 9)
- O, General Correspondence, 1941-44; 1947 (Box 460, Folder 10)
  - Overseas School Committee, 1945-47 (Box 460, Folder 11)
- P-Q, General Correspondence, 1940-44; 1946-47; 1949 (Box 460, Folder 12)
  - Parshley, Howard Madison, 1941-43 (Box 460, Folder 13)
  - Pierce College, 1943-46 (Box 460, Folder 14)
  - President, Secretary to, 1939-43 (Box 460, Folder 15)
  - President's Reports, 1940-41 (Box 460, Folder 16)
  - President's Reports, 1945-46 (Box 460, Folder 17)
  - President's Reports, 1947-48 (Box 460, Folder 18)
  - Public Relations, 1942-48; undated (Box 460, Folder 19)
  - Purchasing Agent, Office of, 1942-49 (Box 460, Folder 20)
- R, General Correspondence, 1941-42 (Box 460, Folder 21)
  - Rally Day, 1943-44 (Box 460, Folder 22)
  - Registrar, Office of, 1942-49 (Box 460, Folder 23)
  - Robert, Osmond T., 1942-44 (Box 460, Folder 24)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1942-44 (Box 460, Folder 25)
  - Royon, Elizabeth, 1944 (Box 460, Folder 26)
- S, General Correspondence, 1940-42; undated (Box 460, Folder 27)
  - Scholarships and Student Aid, 1946-48; undated (Box 460, Folder 28)
  - Scholarships and Student Aid, Russian Scholarship, 1945-46 (Box 460, Folder 29)
  - School for Social Work, 1940-48; undated (Box 460, Folder 30)
  - Scripps College, 1942 (Box 460, Folder 31)
  - Seven College Conference, 1940-42 (Box 461, Folder 1)
  - Seven College Conference, 1943 (Box 461, Folder 2)
  - Seven College Conference, 1944-45 (Box 461, Folder 3)
  - Seven College Conference, 1946-49; undated (Box 461, Folder 4)
  - Students, 1942-49 (Box 461, Folder 5)
  - Students-Male, 1944-48; undated (Box 461, Folder 6)
  - Student Service of America, Inc., 1945-47 (Box 461, Folder 7)
  - Studies, 1943-44 (Box 461, Folder 8)
  - Sweet Briar College, 1942; 1947-48 (Box 461, Folder 9)
- T, General Correspondence, 1942 (Box 461, Folder 10)
  - Treasurer, Office of, 1940-48 (Box 461, Folder 11)
  - Trustees-General, 1940-47 (Box 461, Folder 12)
  - Trustees-Committee on the School for Social Work, 1940-43 (Box 461, Folder 13)
  - Trustees-Comstock, Ada, 1943-49 (Box 461, Folder 14)
  - Trustees-Emerson, Kendall, 1941-44 (Box 461, Folder 15)
  - Trustees-Gleason, Emily (Clapp), 1940-46 (Box 461, Folder 16)
  - Trustees-Hanes, John, 1942-47
  - Trustees-Hofer, Philip, 1941-46
  - Trustees-Hoskins, Harold, 1941-47
  - Trustees-Huntington, Mrs. W. Chapin, 1941-44
  - Trustees-Lord, Mary Pillsbury, 1947
  - Trustees-Lamont, Thomas S., Jr., 1942-48
  - Trustees-Morrow, Elizabeth (Cutter), 1940-47
  - Trustees-Oldham, John E., 1942-44
  - Trustees-Parker, Franklin E., Jr., 1944
  - Trustees-Raymond, Eleanor, 1942
  - Trustees-Stevenson, George S., 1941-44
  - Trustees-Valentine, Alan, 194-43
  - Trustees-Valentine, Lucia (Norton), 1943-44
  - Trustees-Wilson, Mira, 1942-44
  - Trustees-Zinsser, Dorothy (Douglas 1913), 1940-42; 1947
  - Tuition and Fees, 1946-49
- U-V, General Correspondence, 1940-44 (Box 462)
  - Union, 1947-48
  - United States-General, 1942-45; undated
  - United States-Education Office, 1941-42
  - United States-Justice Department, 1942-44
  - United States-Navy Department, 1941-44; undated
  - United States-State Department, 1942-49
  - United States-Treasury Department, 1941-44
  - United States-War Department, 1942-43
  - Universities Center for United Nations Research, 1947-48
  - Vassar College, 1941-48
  - Vocational Office, 1942-49
- W-General Correspondence, 1941-42 (Box 462)
  - Warden, Office of, 1942-47 (Box 462)
  - Wellesley College, 1942-47 (Box 462)
  - Williams, Cora M. (1883), 1942-45 (Box 462)
  - Wilson College, 1944-46 (Box 463, Folder 1)
  - Womens' College Information Board, 1941-43 (Box 463, Folder 2)
  - World Student Service Fund, 1943-44 (Box 463, Folder 3)
  - World War, 1942-46 (Box 463, Folder 4)
  - Wrinch, Dorothy, 1941-44 (Box 463, Folder 5)
- Y-Z, General Correspondence, 1942 (Box 463)
  - Yale University, 1941-43 (Box 463, Folder 7)